

João Pedro Dias

Engineer. Developer. Researcher. Amateur photographer.

Porto, Portugal

☑ jpmdias@fe.up.pt | ₳ jpdias.me | ☑ jpdias | ₲ joaopdias | Ў jpd1as | ₺ jpdias

Summary.

Current Researcher at INESC TEC and pursuing a PhD degree in Informatics Engineering. Graduated from the Integrated Masters in Informatics and Computing Engineering, I'm passionate about technology, with a special focus on security and privacy, web development, data mining & Internet of Things. Besides that, I'm also an amateur photographer, football player, book lover and science addict. **ORCID**: 0000-0001-9066-6436

Education _

Doctoral Program in Informatics Engineering - ProDEI (PhD)

Porto, Portugal

FACULTY OF ENGINEERING OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PORTO (FEUP)

2016-Exp. 2020

· Work under Supervision of Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD and Co-Supervision of João Pascoal Faria, PhD

Master in Informatics and Computing Engineering - MIEIC (MSc)

Porto, Portugal

FACULTY OF ENGINEERING OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PORTO (FEUP)

2011-2016

- GPA: 15 out of 20
- Volunteer at Semana Profissão: Engenheiro (SPE) 2014 & 2016

Sciences and Technologies

Amarante, Porto, Portugal

Externato de Vila Meã

2008-2011

• GPA: 17 out of 20

Work Experience _

Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto

Campus FEUP, Porto, Portugal

INVITED ASSISTANT PROFESSOR

Fev. 2017 - Today

 $\bullet \ \ \text{Teaching practical lectures of Operating Systems and Software Development Laboratories}.$

INESC TEC – Institute for Systems and Computer Engineering, Technology and Science | CSIG – Centre for Information Systems and Computer Graphics

Campus FEUP, Porto, Portugal

RESEARCHER

May 2017 – Today

- Researching in the area of Internet of Things, with special focus on Blockchain and Healthcare applications, in the scope of the project NanoSTIMA: Macro-to-Nano Human Sensing: Towards Integrated Multimodal Health Monitoring and Analytics.
- Project details: nanostima.inesctec.pt

LIACC – Artificial Intelligence and Computer Science Laboratory

University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

RESEARCHER

Sept. 2016 - Apr. 2017

- Researching data representation and data mining applications on railway transportation systems in the scope of the project PEDDIR: Weigth in Motion and Wheels Defect Detection.
- Technologies: MongoDB, Python and Web Development | Project details: www.peddir.eu & www.in2rail.eu

ShiftForward, S.A. Porto, Portugal

SUMMER ENGINEERING INTERN

Jul. 2015 – Aug. 2015

- Development of a Deploy Logger Service, a service for documenting and recording the release of new product versions over time.
- Technologies: Scala and Backbone.js | Project details: shiftforward.github.io/malamute

Centro Hospitalar do Tâmega e Sousa, E.P.E.

Penafiel, Porto, Portugal

IT DEPARTMENT INTERNSHIP

Jul. 2014 - Aug. 2014

- Development of an expedient management system for replacing the existent system based on paper archives.
- Technologies: MySQL and PHP

Teaching

INTEGRATED MASTER IN INFORMATICS AND COMPUTING ENGINEERING · FEUP · 5 YEARS

2018 - 2019 Invited Assistant Professor, Software Development Laboratory · 4th year (First Semester)

- 3 hours per week

2018 - 2019 *Invited Assistant Professor*, **Operating Systems** · 2nd year (Second Semester)

– 4 hours *per* week

2017 - 2018 Invited Assistant Professor, Operating Systems · 2nd year (Second Semester)

- 4 hours per week · 2 classes · 45 students

Publications

CONFERENCE ARTICLES (PEER-REVIEWED)

DYNAMIC ALLOCATION OF SERVERLESS FUNCTIONS IN IOT ENVIRONMENTS

Bucharest, Romania

Duarte Pinto, João Pedro Dias, Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

16th IEEE International Conference on Embedded and Ubiquitous Computing { DOI: To Appear }

A REACTIVE AND MODEL-BASED APPROACH FOR DEVELOPING INTERNET-OF-THINGS SYSTEMS

Coimbra, Portugal

João Pedro Dias, João Pascoal Faria and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

7th Software Engineering Doctoral Symposium (SEDES 2018) – Part of the 11th International Conference on the Quality of Information and Communications Technology (QUATIC'2018) { DOI: 10.1109/QUATIC.2018.00049 }

A BRIEF OVERVIEW OF EXISTING TOOLS FOR TESTING THE INTERNET-OF-THINGS

Västerås, Sweden

João Pedro Dias, Flávio Couto, Ana C.R. Paiva, Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

First International Workshop on Verification and Validation of Internet of Things (VVIoT 2018) – Part of the 11th IEEE Conference on Software Testing, Validation and Verification (ICST 2018) { DOI: 10.1109/ICSTW.2018.00035 }

PATTERNS FOR THINGS THAT FAIL

Vancouver, Canada

António Ramadas, Gil Domingues, João Pedro Dias, Ademar Aguiar, Hugo Sereno Ferreira 24th Conference on Pattern Languages of Programs (PLoP 2017) { DOI: To Appear }

2017

TOWARDS A FRAMEWORK FOR AGENT-BASED SIMULATION OF USER BEHAVIOUR IN E-COMMERCE CONTEXT

Porto, Portugal

Duarte Duarte, João Pedro Dias, Hugo Sereno Ferreira and Zaf. Kokkinogenis

2017

 $15^{th}\ International\ Conference\ on\ Practical\ Applications\ of\ Agents\ and\ Multi-Agent\ Systems\ (PAAMS'17)\ \{\ DOI:\ 10.1007/978-3-319-61578-3_3\ \}$

AUTOMATING THE EXTRACTION OF STATIC CONTENT AND DYNAMIC BEHAVIOUR FROM E-COMMERCE WEBSITES

Madeira, Portugal

João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2017

8th International Conference on Ambient Systems, Networks and Technologies (ANT'17) { DOI: 10.1016/j.procs.2017.05.355 }

A HANDS-ON APPROACH ON BOTNETS FOR BEHAVIOR EXPLORATION

Porto, Portugal

João Pedro Dias, José Pedro Pinto and José Magalhães Cruz

2017

2nd International Conference on Internet of Things, Big Data and Security (IoTBDS 2017) { DOI: 10.5220/0006392404630469 }

INFORMAL PUBLICATIONS & OTHERS

A PRELIMINARY STUDY ON MESH NETWORKS AND IOT

Porto, Portugal

Filipa Barros, Luis Sousa, João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

11th Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2018)

AUTOMATING THE EXTRACTION OF STATIC CONTENT AND DYNAMIC BEHAVIOUR FROM

João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

E-COMMERCE WEBSITES

2017

Porto, Portugal

10th Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2017)

A HANDS-ON APPROACH ON BOTNETS FOR A LEARNING PURPOSE

Porto, Portugal

João Pedro Dias, José Pedro Pinto and José Magalhães Cruz

2016

9th Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2016)

DISSERTATIONS

REVERSE ENGINEERING STATIC CONTENT AND DYNAMIC BEHAVIOUR OF E-COMMERCE SITES FOR FUN AND PROFIT

Porto, Portugal

SUPERVISED BY HUGO SERENO FERREIRA | GRADE OF 17 OUT OF 20.

Master's Dissertation, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { ID: 10216/85374 }

2016

Educational & Scientific Activities _____

MASTER'S DISSERTATION CO-SUPERVISING

2017	DYNAMIC ALLOCATION OF SERVERLESS FUNCTIONS IN IOT ENVIRONMENTS by Duarte	Porto, Portugal
- 2018	Pinto, Supervised by Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD, Masters in Informatics and	
2010	Computing Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { ID: 10216/114149 }	
2017	BLOCKCHAIN AS A PKI FOR OWNERSHIP CONTROL OF IOT DEVICES by Guilherme Pinto,	Porto, Portugal
- 2018	Supervised by Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD, Masters in Informatics and Computing	
2010	Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { ID: 10216/114144 }	
2016	Interoperability In Software Applications For Smart Cities: Towards A	Porto, Portugal
2017	REFERENCE ARCHITECTURE by José Pedro Pinto, Supervised by Rosaldo Rossetti,	
	PhD, Masters in Informatics and Computing Engineering, Faculty of Engineering,	

PROGRAM COMMITTEES & REVIEWS

University of Porto { ID: 10216/107529 }

2017	PC Member , IEEE S3C 2017 - 2017 IEEE Summer School on Smart Cities	Natal, Brazil
2017	IEEE Intelligent Vehicles Symposium (IEEE IV'17), Reviewer	California, USA
2017	IEEE 20th International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems (IEEE	Yokohama, Japan
	ITSC 2017), Reviewer	

Conference Organization

2018	Student Volunteer , XP 2018 – 19 th International Conference on Agile Software	Porto, Portugal
	Development	
2018	Conference Organization Chair, DSIE'18 – 13 th Doctoral Symposium in Informatics	Porto, Portugal
	Engineering	
2018	Advisor Board Member, Talk a Bit – Technology Conference, 6th Edition (2018)	Porto, Portugal
2017	Student Volunteer (Media Coverage) , EPIA 2017 – 18 th EPIA Conference on Artificial	Porto, Portugal
	Intelligence	
2017	Web Communication Co-chair, ACM CarSys 2017 – The Second ACM International	Utah, USA
	Workshop on Smart, Autonomous, and Connected Vehicular Systems and Services, part	
	of the The 23 rd Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking	
	(MobiCom 2017)	
2017	Advisor Board Member, Talk a Bit – Technology Conference, 5th Edition (2017)	Porto, Portugal
2016	Conference Chair, Talk a Bit – Technology Conference, 4th Edition (2016)	Porto, Portugal
2016	Web Communication Co-chair, 2016 IEEE 19th International Conference on Intelligent	Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
	Transportation Systems (ITSC 2016)	
2014	Student Volunteer , Inter-University Programming Marathon (MIUP 2014)	Porto, Portugal
2014	Student Volunteer , INForum - Symposion on Informatics (INForum 2014)	Porto, Portugal

Invited Talks & Workshops _____

Information Systems and Software Engineering Seminars (SESI & SES)

HOSTED AT FACULTY OF ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF PORTO FOR STUDENTS OF THE MIEIC & MESW DEGREES

• **Seminar**: How to Kill Your Privacy and IoT Your Home Along the Way.

Pixels Camp 2017

HOSTED BY BRIGHT PIXEL AND BETA-I

Sept. 2017

• Workshop: PiHeadquarters or How to Take Control of your House with Raspberry Pi and Docker.

Lisboa, Portugal Sept. 2017

JCP1. 2011

Porto, Portugal

HOSTED BY BLIP.PT Apr. 2016

• **Presentation**: A hands-on approach on botnets for a learning purpose.

Share World Seminar 2015 – "Europe vs. Asia: Grass Is Always Greener On The Other Side"

FEUP, Porto, Portugal

HOSTED BY SHARE GLOBAL STUDENT THINK TANK

March 2015

• Workshop: How To Create Your First Personal Webpage.

Additional Training _____

2018	1st UPTEC School on the Future of Computing, UPTEC – Science and Technology Park	FBAUP, Porto, Portugal
	of University of Porto	
2017	CyberTalk: Security - Business Enablement, Multicert - Electronic Certification	FEUP, Porto, Portugal
	Services, S.A.	
2017	Project Management, ERASMUS+ Mobility for teaching	FEUP, Porto, Portugal
2016	AWS Technical Essentials Online, Amazon Web Services – Training and Certification	Online
2015	Practical Workshop in Agile Project Management, Strongstep - Innovation in	UPTEC, Porto, Portugal
	Software Quality	
2015	CERN Spring Campus, CERN - European Organization for Nuclear Research	Lisbon, Portugal
2014	M101JS: MongoDB for Node.js Developers, MongoDB University	Online

Skills & Languages ___

Programming
Python ■ Node.JS ■ C/C++ ■ Scala ■ Java ■ C# ■ PHP ■

Web Technologies
HTML5 ■ CSS ■ JavaScript ■ Laravel(PHP) ■ Flask(Python) ■ Bootstrap(CSS) ■ jQuery(JS) ■

Databases
MySQL ■ PostgreSQL ■ InfluxDB ■ MongoDB ■

Arduino ■ Git ■ Android ■ Windows Apps ■ Docker ■ LaTeX ■

Languages
Portuguese (Mother-tongue) ■ English ■

Pro Bono Activity

ACADEMIC

IEEE University of Porto Student Branch

Porto, Portugal

STUDENT MEMBER

2012 – Today

EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE (SECRETARY)

2013 – 2015

- As a voluntary member I had organized and co-organized some workshops (*C#*, *Photography*, *ET_EX*, *Web Development*) and other events including *IEEE Day*, *IEEEXtreme* and *IEEEmadC*.
- As secretary I was also responsable for mantain the minutes of all meetings and other paperwork.

HUMANITARIAN

Luz da Vida Youth Group

Amarante, Porto, Portugal

FOUNDER MEMBER

2009 – 2011

· Founder and former active member, I had taken part of large number of activities on behalf of the village community.

Honors & Awards

INTERNATIONAL

2018	427 th (of 3350), IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 11.0, <i>ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2017	847 th (of 2815), Google Hash Code 2017, hashcode.withgoogle.com	Online – Porto, Portugal
2015	189th (of 2477) , IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 9.0, <i>ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2014	Honorable Mention , IEEEmadC – Mobile Application Dev. Contest, <i>ieeemadc.org</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2013	126th (of 2570) , IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 7.0, <i>ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2013	2nd Place , European BEST Engineering Competition, <i>ebec.best.eu.org</i>	Warsaw, Poland

DOMESTIC

2011 1st Place, PmatE Mat12 – Mathematics Competition, *pmate.ua.pt* 2009 2nd Place, PmatE Fis12 – Physics Competition, *pmate.ua.pt*

University of Aveiro, Portugal University of Aveiro, Portugal

Interests & Hobbies _____

F.A.D.A. Amateur League

GRUPO DESPORTIVO E RECREATIVO DE TRAVANCA

2016 - 2017

Amateur Photographer

NATURE, LANDSCAPE, URBAN EXPLORATION, EVENTS

2008 – Today

- 2010 Exposition at Movimento d'Artes, Travanca, Amarante, Portugal Promoted by the Cooperativa Cultural Vinha das Artes
- 2018 Finalist at the Norte Multimédia Contest Photography Category Promoted by the Norte Portugal Regional Coordination and Development Commission (CCDR-N)
- 2018 Finalist at the PORTUGAL NUM ISQUEIRO BIC® Contest Promoted by the I Love My BIC initiative by BIC Portugal